<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fernando Caballero | You Soft Matter Group</title>
    <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/author/fernando-caballero/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zhihongyou.github.io/author/fernando-caballero/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Fernando Caballero</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zhihongyou.github.io/media/icon_hu294d7ef0a71614cd9e4bcc2cc7f71769_229318_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Fernando Caballero</title>
      <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/author/fernando-caballero/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vorticity Phase Separation and Defect Lattices in the Isotropic Phase of Active Liquid Crystals</title>
      <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/caballero-23-vortic-phase-separ-defec-lattic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/caballero-23-vortic-phase-separ-defec-lattic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use numerical simulations and linear stability analysis to study the dynamics of an active liquid crystal film on a substrate in the regime where the passive system would be isotropic. Extensile activity builds up local orientational order and  destabilizes the quiescent isotropic state above a critical activity value, eventually resulting in spatiotemporal chaotic dynamics akin to the one observed ubiquitously in the nematic state. Here we show that tuning substrate friction yields a variety of emergent structures at intermediate activity, including lattices of flow vortices with associated regular arrangements of topological defects and a new state where flow vortices trap pairs of $+1/2$ defect that chase each other tail. \mcmrev{These chiral units spontaneously pick the sense of rotation and organize in a hexagonal lattice, surrounded by a diffuse flow of opposite rotation to maintain zero net vorticity.} The length scale of these emergent structures is set by the screening length $l_\eta=\sqrt{\eta/\Gamma}$ of the flow, controlled by the shear viscosity  $\eta$ and the substrate friction $\Gamma$, and can be captured by simple mode selection of the vortical flows. We demonstrate that the emergence of coherent structures can be interpreted as a phase separation of vorticity, where friction plays a role akin to that of birth/death processes in breaking conservation of the phase separating species and selecting a characteristic scale for the patterns. Our work shows that friction provides an experimentally accessible tuning parameter for designing controlled active flows.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
