<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M. Cristina Marchetti | You Soft Matter Group</title>
    <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/author/m.-cristina-marchetti/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zhihongyou.github.io/author/m.-cristina-marchetti/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>M. Cristina Marchetti</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zhihongyou.github.io/media/icon_hu294d7ef0a71614cd9e4bcc2cc7f71769_229318_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>M. Cristina Marchetti</title>
      <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/author/m.-cristina-marchetti/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Active Liquid Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/adkins-22-dynam-activ-liquid-inter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/adkins-22-dynam-activ-liquid-inter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Controlling interfaces of phase-separating fluid mixtures is key to the creation of diverse functional soft materials. Traditionally, this is accomplished with surface-modifying chemical agents. Using experiment and theory, we studied how mechanical activity shapes soft interfaces that separate an active and a passive fluid. Chaotic flows in the active fluid give rise to giant interfacial fluctuations and noninertial propagating active waves. At high activities, stresses disrupt interface continuity and drive droplet generation, producing an emulsion-like active state composed of finite-sized droplets. When in contact with a solid boundary, active interfaces exhibit nonequilibrium wetting transitions, in which the fluid climbs the wall against gravity. These results demonstrate the promise of mechanically driven interfaces for creating a new class of soft active matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When active and passive fluids interact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incompatible liquids such as oil and water will phase separate with low interfacial tension. Adkins et al. investigated the dynamics of a one-dimensional interface separating an active nematic phase with a passive isotropic phase (see the Perspective by Palacci). They found a rich behavior of fluctuating interfaces in which the phase-separating fluids could form active emulsions that did not coarsen and in which droplets formed spontaneously. Macroscopic interfaces can also displayed propagating waves with a characteristic wave number and speed. Furthermore, the activity of one of the fluids, in which the addition of energy drove the ordering of that fluid, was able to modify the wetting transitions. The authors also observed active wetting of a solid surface whereby active extensile stresses parallel to the surface drove the fluid to climb a solid wall against gravity. —MSL&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Active nematic defects in compressible and incompressible flows</title>
      <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/pokawanvit-22-acti-nema-defe-comp-incom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/pokawanvit-22-acti-nema-defe-comp-incom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study two-dimensional active nematics on a substrate, comparing compressible and incompressible flows. Through simulations and theoretical analysis we show that arch patterns are stable in the compressible case but are unstable in an incompressible system. For compressible flows at high activity, stable arches organize in a smectic-like pattern, with associated global polar order of +1/2 nematic defects. By contrast, incompressible flows give rise to local nematic order of the +1/2 defects, consisting of anti-aligned pairs of neighboring defects, as previously established.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocity As a Generic Route To Traveling States</title>
      <link>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/you-20-nonrec-as-gener-route-to-travel-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhihongyou.github.io/publication/you-20-nonrec-as-gener-route-to-travel-states/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We examine a nonreciprocally coupled dynamical model of a mixture of two diffusing species. We demonstrate that nonreciprocity, which is encoded in the model via antagonistic cross-diffusivities, provides a generic mechanism for the emergence of traveling patterns in purely diffusive systems with conservative dynamics. In the absence of nonreciprocity, the binary fluid mixture undergoes a phase transition from a homogeneous mixed state to a demixed state with spatially separated regions rich in one of the two components. Above a critical value of the parameter tuning nonreciprocity, the static demixed pattern acquires a finite velocity, resulting in a state that breaks both spatial and time-reversal symmetry, as well as the reflection parity of the static pattern. We elucidate the generic nature of the transition to traveling patterns using a minimal model that can be studied analytically. Our work has direct relevance to nonequilibrium assembly in mixtures of chemically interacting colloids that are known to exhibit nonreciprocal effective interactions, as well as to mixtures of active and passive agents where traveling states of the type predicted here have been observed in simulations. It also provides insight on transitions to traveling and oscillatory states seen in a broad range of nonreciprocal systems with nonconservative dynamics, from reaction–diffusion and prey–predators models to multispecies mixtures of microorganisms with antagonistic interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significance&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective interactions that break action–reaction symmetry are ubiquitous in systems where interactions are mediated by a nonequilibrium environment. They are also the norm in the living world. By examining the dynamics of a diffusing binary mixture, we demonstrate that antagonistic cross-diffusivities can drive the transition from static to traveling spatial patterns. In the context of an analytically tractable model, we elucidate the nature of the transition and demonstrate that the emergence of traveling or oscillating patterns is a generic consequence of nonreciprocity in multispecies systems described by scalar fields. Our work is directly relevant to the understanding and control of nonequilibrium assembly in mixtures of chemically interacting colloids.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
